{"tossups": [{"question": "Edward VII once visited this man\u2019s summer estate of Clifton, where he often met with Union officials. Benjamin Moore was an early business partner of this man who used Conestoga wagons to run a wholesaling business. This Quaker made the bulk of his fortune in the railroad industry before allocating $7 million in his bequest for the establishment of an orphanage, hospital, and institution that bears his name. For ten points, name this philanthropist who established a namesake university in Baltimore.", "answer": "Johns <b><u>Hopkins</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At the beginning of these wars, six legions successfully defeated and subdued the Helvetii [[hel-WEH-tih-ee]] tribe at Bibracte [[bee-BRAHK-teh]]. To support the Ubii [[OOH-bih-ee]] during these wars, a general built movable wooden bridges to retaliate against raiding tribes across the Rhine River. A member of the First Triumvirate recorded his victory over Vercingetorix [[ver-sin-JEH-tuh-riks]] at the Siege of Alesia during these wars. Julius Caesar wrote <em>Commentaries on</em>, for ten points, what set of \u201cwars'' during which Rome conquered modern-day France?", "answer": "<b><u>Gallic</u></b> Wars (accept <b><u>Roman Conquest of Gaul</u></b> or equivalents)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "An interruption in the flow of this work featured an interlude by Ram\u00f3n Raquello [[rah-KWEH-yoh]] and his Orchestra. In this work, a disturbance at Grover's Mill leads to the exclamation \u201cGood Heavens\u201d after the appearance of a figure resembling a \u201cgray snake.\u201d The Mercury Theater created an updated version of a text that formed the basis of this 1938 work, which was meant to coincide with Halloween. Mass panic resulted from the airing of, for ten points, what radio drama by Orson Welles detailing an alien invasion?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>War of the Worlds</u></b></em> radio drama broadcast", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "In a dissent in this case, one Justice claimed that the central entity was \u201cnot simply another 'idea' or 'point of view' competing for recognition in the marketplace of ideas.\u201d The defendant in this case was a member of the Revolutionary Communist Youth Brigade who engaged in the central action during the 1984 Republican National Convention protests. Prior to this case, 48 states banned the desecration of the central object. For ten points, name this Supreme Court case which overturned laws against the burning of the American flag.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Texas v.</u></b> Gregory Lee</em> <em><b><u>Johnson</u></b></em> (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This procedure was originally developed to provide a source of ammonia for explosives, and the wife of this procedure's primary creator is thought to have killed herself over guilt at her husband's involvement in Germany's chemical warfare program. Both men for whom this process is named received Nobel Prizes, the first for its discovery in 1918 and the second for expanding its scale in 1931. For ten points, name this nitrogen fixation process which consumes more than one percent of humanity's energy production and helps feed one third of the world's population.", "answer": "<b><u>Haber</u></b>-Bosch Process", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This man examined corruption in San Francisco\u2019s Office of Economic Opportunity in a work often paired with another chronicling a meeting that Leonard Bernstein hosted for the Black Panthers. Chuck Yeager claims that a monkey will be the first traveler in the Mercury Program in a speech dramatized by this man in a book centered on the Space Race. Ken Kesey\u2019s LSD use is central to another work by this author titled <em>The Electric Kool-Aid</em> <em>Acid Test</em>. For ten points, name this proponent of New Journalism who wrote <em>The Right Stuff</em>.", "answer": "Tom <b><u>Wolfe</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "In a defense against treason to the crown, this man claimed, \"Life, without the dignity of an intelligent being, is not worth having.\" This man founded the Exovedate [[eks-oh-veh-DAHT]], though his men lost at the Battles of Fish Creek and Batoche [[bah-TOHSH]]. Big Bear and Gabriel Dumont joined this man, who was the only parliament member to miss the Pacific Scandal debate. John A. MacDonald ordered this man's trial in Regina [[reh-JAI-nah]] after the Northwest Rebellion. For ten points, name this Manitoban M\u00e9tis [[MEH-tee]] leader.", "answer": "Louis \"David\" <b><u>Riel</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ballet's eight movements were included on Bill Frisell\u2019s album \u201cHave a Little Faith.\u201d This ballet was commissioned by Lincoln Kerstein and was premiered in 1938 by a company headed by Eugene Loring. Tunes including \u201cGreat Grandad\u201d and \u201cGoodbye Old Paint\u201d appear in this ballet, which opens and closes with a theme titled \u201cThe Open Prairie.\u201d A song about the \u201cOld Chisholm Trail\u201d appears in this ballet, in which the title character steals a warden's gun and escapes jail before being shot and killed. For ten points, name this Aaron Copland ballet about a Wild West outlaw.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Billy the Kid</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "Jaroslava Moserov\u00e1 [[yah-roh-SLAH-vah moh-seh-roh-VAH]] was a burns specialist who treated one patient after this event whose actions were followed by those of M\u00e1rton Moyses and Evzen Plocek [[PLOH-chek]]. This event was caused by the enactment of a program during Victorious February which led to liberalization in the Action Programme, referred to as \"Socialism with a human face.\" Jan Palach [[YAHN pah-LAHK]] immolated himself after this event. For ten points, name these 1968 reforms by Alexander Dub\u010dek [[DOOB-chek]] in Czechoslovakia.", "answer": "<b><u>Prague Spring</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pra\u017esk\u00e9 jaro</u></b>; accept <b><u>Pra\u017esk\u00e1 jar</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A 1964 Supreme Court decision dealt with the constitutionality of whether this state could prohibit theaters from running Louis Malle\u2019s film <em>The Lovers</em>. A case originating in this state gave rise to the \u201cimminent lawless action\u201d test and arose after a reporter was asked to cover a KKK rally. The <em>Brandenburg</em> case arose in this state which was found to be subject to the exclusionary rule. The Supreme Court ruled that prosecutors could not use evidence obtained in violation of the Fourth Amendment in, for ten points, what state, the defendant in the <em>Mapp</em> case?", "answer": "<b><u>Ohio</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "It is not Andrew Carnegie, but this man made a $400,000 donation for the creation of a library now symbolized by a pair of lion statues. Thurlow Weed headed a political group named for this man\u2019s \u201cHouse,\" which was the first luxury hotel in the United States. Fort George was a trading post renamed for this man, who is considered the U.S.'s first multi-millionaire. Making his initial fortune along the Pacific Coast selling pelts of a fashionable animal and smuggling opium into China, for ten points, who was this early-American tycoon?", "answer": "John Jacob <b><u>Astor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man conducted experiments at a camp he named for his former assistant, Jesse Lazear. Findings by this man led to a series of failed inoculations conducted by William C. Gorgas at the behest of Leonard Wood. This man built on Carlos Finlay\u2019s idea that direct contact was not the cause of one disease, and this American showed that swamp-ridden paths taken by enlisted soldiers correlated with incidence of a disease which affected many working on the Panama Canal. For ten points, name this doctor who verified that mosquitoes transmitted yellow fever.", "answer": "Walter <b><u>Reed</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Just prior to this man's execution, he allegedly told his executioners, \"Soldiers! Do your duty! Straight to the heart but spare the face. Fire!\" This subject of a work by Alexandre Dumas p\u00e8re was ordered to retrieve a set of forty cannons from the plains of Sablons [[sah-BLOHN]] on 13 Vend\u00e9miaire [[von-deh-MYEHR]], resulting in an incident in which Royalist forces were given a \u201cwhiff of grapeshot.\u201d Through his marriage to Caroline, this man became brother-in-law to a man who made him king of Naples. For ten points, name this admiral and marshal under Napoleon.", "answer": "Joachim <b><u>Murat</u></b> [[joh-ah-SHAHM moo-RAH]] (be lenient on pronunciation)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A series of accusations were launched against one group in this country following the murder of Mikhail Rybachenko in its city of Dub\u0103sari [[doo-bah-SAHD]]. One incident in this modern-day country was the subject of Hayim Bialik\u2019s poem \u201cIn the City of Slaughter.\u201d The Uganda Scheme was promoted by Theodor Herzl in the aftermath of a 1903 pogrom in the capital of this country, whose city of Tiraspol [[tee-RAHS-pohl]] became part of its breakaway state of Transnistria. For ten points, name this Eastern European country which, in 2020, elected its first female president, Maia Sandu.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Moldova</u></b> (or Republica <b><u>Moldova</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An inventor from this family created PET plastic bottles while working at DuPont. Another member of this family drew a self portrait titled <em>Pumpkinhead - Self-Portrait</em>, which is based on his father's <em>Trodden Weed</em> portrait. This family worked in Chadds Ford, Pennsylvania, and included a painter who created 247 studies of Helga Testorf. Howard Pyle trained a member of this family, who illustrated <em>Treasure Island</em> and was named N.C.  For ten points, name this family which included the painter of <em>Christina's World</em>, Andrew.", "answer": "<b><u>Wyeth</u></b> (accept Andrew <b><u>Wyeth</u></b>, N.C. <b><u>Wyeth</u></b>, Jamie <b><u>Wyeth</u></b>, or Nathaniel <b><u>Wyeth</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "St. Francis of Assisi unsuccessfully tried to convert the fifth leader of this dynasty, whose pleas for peace were undermined by Pelagius [[peh-LAY-jee-us]]. The killing of Turanshah is often seen as the de facto end of this dynasty\u2019s reign, after which it was nominally headed by a puppet of Aybak. This dynasty came to power following the death of Nur al-Din of the Zengids, and its founder signed the Treaty of Jaffa to end a campaign that included fighting at Arsuf and the Horns of Hattin. The Third Crusade was fought by, for ten points, what Islamic dynasty led by Saladin?", "answer": "<b><u>Ayyubid</u></b> dynasty (accept <b><u>Ayyubid</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A member of this family named Christopher commanded the <em>General Greene</em> during the Quasi-War. Another member of this family helped Winfield Scott carry out the Siege of Veracruz during the Mexican-American War before travelling aboard the \u201cBlack Ships\u201d in an example of gunboat diplomacy. That man was the brother of a member of this family who was inspired by the last words of James Lawrence to print \u201cDon\u2019t Give Up the Ship\u201d on his flag. For ten points, a commodore who was sent to Japan and the winner of the Battle of Lake Erie were both members of what family?", "answer": "<b><u>Perry</u></b> (accept Christopher Raymond <b><u>Perry</u></b>; accept Oliver Hazard <b><u>Perry</u></b>; accept Matthew C(albraith) <b><u>Perry</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, one man was threatened that his son Lord Strange would be killed if he didn\u2019t join one side, prompting him to state that he had other sons. A chronicle by Raphael Holinshed led to the belief that this battle was fought at Ambion Hill. The Duke of Norfolk and the Earl of Northumberland commanded two of the three groups on one side in this battle, at which the Stanleys assisted the eventual winner. The Plantagenet dynasty\u2019s rule of England ended with the death of the Yorkist king at, for ten points, what 1485 battle during the Wars of the Roses?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Bosworth</u></b> Field", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>John Tyler\u2019s admiration for this figure\u2019s speaking ability prompted him to</u></b> <b><u>state, \"I would like to hand Mr. Calhoun over to you.\" A \"Sermon to the Medical</u></b> <b><u>Students\" was delivered by this person, who one reporter described as the (+)</u></b> <b>\u201cLioness of the [World Anti-Slavery] Convention.\" This Quaker was invited by Jane Hunt to a meeting where she helped (*) </b>draft the Declaration of Sentiments. For ten points, name this women\u2019s rights activist who, with Elizabeth Cady Stanton, organized the Seneca Falls Convention.", "answer": "Lucretia <b><u>Mott</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One side in this conflict threatened to burn down a city in the Brunswick</u></b> <b><u>Manifesto if the royal monarchy of one country was harmed. During this conflict, a</u></b> <b><u>Dutch force at Neerwinden [[NEER-vin-dun]] repulsed an attack led by Charles</u></b> <b><u>Fran\u00e7ois (+)</u> Dumouriez [[doo-moor-YEH]]. The Declaration of Pillnitz was signed by Leopold II a year prior to this conflict, which partly caused the September Massacres. The Treaty of (*) </b>Campo Formio ended this conflict, which began after a declaration of war on Austria in 1792. For ten points, name this conflict between a group of European powers and France.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>First Coalition</u></b> (accept Guerre de la <b><u>Premi\u00e8re Coalition</u></b>; prompt on \"French Revolution\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Fritz Joubert Duquesne [[zhoo-BEHR doo-KEHN]] escaped from a prison in this</u></b> <b><u>territory, and in 2020, the first woman and first person of African heritage was</u></b> <b><u>appointed governor of this territory when Queen Elizabeth named (+)</u> Rena Lalgie to the role. After St. John\u2019s and Jamestown, this territory\u2019s town of St. (*) </b>George\u2019s was considered the earliest successful British-American settlement. Compass difficulties legendarily plague ships travelling in a region named for, for ten points, what British Overseas territory in the Atlantic?", "answer": "Islands of <b><u>Bermuda</u></b> (or The <b><u>Somers Isles</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man wrote that the Jews were \u201cthe most unpleasant race ever heard of\u201d in</u></b> <b><u>a survey of religion titled</u> </b><em><b><u>Treatise on the Gods</u></b></em><b><u>. This man created two classes known</u></b> <b><u>as \"demagogues\" and \"demaslaves\" in his critique of (*)</u> democracy. This man co-founded a publication that once employed William F. Buckley, and this founder of </b><em><b>The </b><b>American Mercury</b></em><b> worked for the (*) </b><em>Baltimore Sun</em> when he accused a schoolteacher of being an \u201cinfidel\u201d during a 1925 case. For ten points, name this journalist and satirist who coined the term \"Scopes Monkey Trial.\"", "answer": "H(enry) L(ouis) <b><u>Mencken</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of the first teams with this status was started by Octavius Catto and Jacob</u></b> <b><u>C. White, Jr. and was called the \"Pythians.\" Happy Chandler was open to his league</u></b> <b><u>working with teams and leagues with this status, but (+)</u> Kennesaw Mountain Landis had earlier prevented it. Leagues with this status featured star players including Judy Johnson, Oscar Charleston, and (*) </b>Josh Gibson. For ten points, what status was shared by a variety of leagues that began to lose popularity and influence after the Brooklyn Dodgers brought Jackie Robinson to baseball's Major Leagues?", "answer": "<b><u>Negro</u></b> league(s) baseball (accept descriptive answers indicating baseball teams or leagues with only <b><u>Black</u></b> players or players of <b><u>African</u></b> descent)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>Feudalism in this dynasty began at the Council of Liubech. Orphans were</u></b> <b><u>protected in this dynasty by the Izgoi, while the \"ladder,\" or rota, ranked princes. A</u></b> <b><u>member of this dynasty murdered Drevlians at a feast with flaming sparrows. This</u></b> <b><u>dynasty's last ruler was called the (+)</u> Bellringer, and its members included Saints Boris and Gleb. Izyaslav [[EEZ-yah-slahf]], Svyatoslav [[svai-AHT-oh-slahf]], and Vsevolod [[vuh-SAY-vuh-lud]] were three heads of this dynasty after (*) </b>Yaroslav the Wise of Kiev died. Descended from a Viking chieftain, for ten points, what Russian dynasty preceded the Romanovs?", "answer": "<b><u>Rurik</u></b>id Dynasty (accept <b><u>Rurik</u></b>ids; accept <b><u>Rurik</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>William Lowe was elected to Congress while running under this party, which</u></b> <b><u>may have been founded at a convention in Indianapolis. One of this party\u2019s early</u></b> <b><u>presidential nominees was the inventor of the first American locomotive,</u> </b><em><b><u>Tom</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Thumb</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> Peter Cooper ran for president under this party, as did James Weaver in 1880. This party condemned one act as the \u201cCrime of 73\u201d and called for the reversal of the (*) </b>Specie Resumption Act of 1875. For ten points, name this short-lived political party often named after a word for paper currency.", "answer": "<b><u>Greenback</u></b> Party (accept <b><u>Greenback</u></b>s; accept <b><u>National Independent</u></b> Party; accept <b><u>Greenback</u></b> Labor Party)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This politician introduced the Council of Four Hundred, made of</u> </b><em><b><u>strategoi</u></b></em><b><u>,</u></b> <em><b><u>archons</u></b></em><b><u>, and other prominent citizens. A law passed by this man forced exile upon</u></b> <b><u>any person who killed another citizen, whether (+)</u> or not it was intentional. This statesman instituted a law forcing debtors into slavery in a Greek city-state, and his name has become (*) </b>synonymous with the term for \u201charsh punishment.\" For ten points, name this Athenian politician, the first to pass a set of comprehensive laws in Greece.", "answer": "<b><u>Draco</u></b>n (accept <b><u>Draco</u></b>nian)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Many languages in a family named for this culture share words like</u> </b><em><b><u>kava</u></b></em><b><u>, a</u></b> <b><u>plant traditionally ground or pounded. This culture\u2019s site of Mata o le Alelo is where</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Sina fell in love with an eel which once held the title of Tui Viti. Using a magical hook made of ancestor bones, a trickster figure of these people raised an (*) </b>archipelago. For ten points, name this culture of the Pacific whose divine figures include Maui and Pele.", "answer": "<b><u>Polynesia</u></b>ns (accept more specific cultures like <b><u>Hawaii</u></b>ans, <b><u>Tahiti</u></b>ans, or <b><u>Samoa</u></b>ns)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}], "bonuses": []}